Nice.
Well, hello. Hi, Ian, and
welcome back to the select committee.
I know that this briefing has been a long time coming, with a few
bits and pieces happening, and this committee being quite busy with
RMA reform. But welcome to the committee this
afternoon. We look forward to your presentation.
And look, really, we are in your hands.
We have got the documents and if you want to talk us
through your presentation.
Thank you very much. Chris will start us off, and yeah, we'll take it
from there. Thank you so much, Catherine, for finding us the time,
and a whole lot of thank yous around the room for the support for this piece
of work.
So kia ora. My name's Chris Ingle. I'm with the Bay of Plenty Regional
Council as a day job, as one of the general managers.
But for this role, I'm the chair of the reference
group that supports Ian both for his academic work and
his research for the future of biodiversity in New Zealand.
And with me is
Brent Mountford. I'll let these guys introduce themselves.
Yeah. Yes, I'm on the reference group as well, and sheep and beef farmer
up in the Bay. And as most of you most probably know,
quite a conservationist, right into that sort of thing.
Which bay was that?
The real bay.
The real bay, that's right. Well, actually, I think we lost last one.
Oh, Hawke's safe.
Looking to get that back. Yeah,
and also president for Federated Farmers Bay of Plenty.
Ian Herbert. I am the New Zealand Biophin
assessment lead.
This assessment is being done independently through the Otago
University Business School, where I'm completing my Doctor of
Business Administration. If you're to take all of the
Master of Business Administration people, all the MBAs, and find the
quirky ones, they're the ones who go on and do a doctorate.
So this work is done as part of that doctorate.
So thank you all very much for your time.
I just want to also just acknowledge Peter,
who's in the back, from the Parliamentary Commissioner for the Environment.
Over the last two and a half years of this assessment,
we've been able to reach out to them,
just to let them know what we're doing, and they've been able to give us
a
bit of feedback, and so want to acknowledge
them. Also want to acknowledge a few
members of Parliament who in the past have helped with this and understand
the numbers. First of all, of course, is the Prime Minister, who does know
the numbers behind the fund that we're talking about.
Also would like to acknowledge Chris Hipkins,
who
has said, "Yep, keen to keep this on our radar."
Shane Jones has asked Andy Foster to keep it on his radar.
Want to also acknowledge Simon Court,
who understood the importance of having a natural capital policy to go
with this.
Plus Lan Pham, who is not here, who has a good
understanding of this. So I just wanted to acknowledge those people before we
start.
So, in terms of the purpose, we'll just go to the next slide.
It is very straightforward. It is to measure
New Zealand's biodiversity investment,
calculate the gap between
what it takes to maintain and restore our
biodiversity across the country,
and then reduce the deferrals. A deferral is
a financial input into that
purpose,
and it's deferred to the next year.
So we're looking at reducing deferrals on natural capital.
So that's what a Biofin purpose is.
It uses biodiversity finance to break the
historic cycle of biodiversity loss.
So it's non-regulatory.
And if we go to the next slide.
And just, members, we've only got 14 slides, so what we were hoping to do was
to fly through them fairly quickly,
and then have some pretty free-ranging questions and answers.
And Ian's here to answer all the questions, although Brent might have some answers
too. But some of these slides you may have seen if you were here at the last time
we presented about a year ago. And this
picture here shows how many countries in the
world, 133 nations in the world, are following this identical
process, the Biofin process. So this isn't something that Ian's
dreamed up in the University of Otago, although I'm sure he could
if we set him to that task. But this is actually a tried and true
process that's been adopted,
perhaps mostly in the countries like Africa, South America, but now it's
also being adopted in European countries as well.
So I think New Zealand's well-placed now to be doing this work.
There's a toolbox of, I think, 150 different finance
solutions, and you can select which one suits your nation.
And once you've gone through this process, then it becomes obvious which ones
are going to work, and that's Ian's job in this research.
So the next
slide shows the process that Brent and I and the other four
members of the reference group are trying to follow. Well, we are following it.
And it's basically that the diagram there with the three in the middle,
the arrow, if you like.
With these three reports that have to be done to satisfy these requirements, and
the first is already completed, the policy and institutional
review.
If you haven't read it, it's really just reflecting the laws of this
country and how we deliver biodiversity currently.
And of course, that's changing, as you guys are well aware.
The second one, which we're reporting back on today, is the biodiversity
expenditure review, and that's perhaps the most comprehensive
review that's ever been done. Although I understand PCE have done a
similar one as well, which has
come out with the same
sort of patterns.
So that's what we're reporting back today, and then the next piece of work that
we've still got to complete is the financial needs assessment that we're planning
for at the moment. So once those three pieces of work are done,
we can tick this off and say we've done a good job, and so far, so good.
We're two-thirds of the way through.
On the right, there's just a wee diagram of how the reference group interacts
with assessment team, and there's a huge working group that Ian has as well
of ecologists and other experts from around New Zealand that help him with
problem-solving.
And next slide.
Thank you.
So thank you, Chris. Just to expand on the working group.
So that's governmental, non-governmental, finance
experts,
biodiversity experts. There's about
26 of us on the working group, and we pull on the different skill sets
as required as we go through the process.
It's quite important for us to say it's not a musical
instrument, and it's not larger than life.
Yep, and it's not a science. It's biodiversity finance.
Keep one eye on the end game. As the economy grows, investment
in biodiversity grows.
And so
what I wanted to talk about here
is simply
where, if we had biodiversity
investment tracking with economic growth, which is what we're
suggesting as part of sustainable development,
you'd have the light blue bars.
What the fund will do will help us do more of that
as move transition more towards sustainable development by
investing in biodiversity as the economy grows.
And so it's an economic approach.
The dark blue bars are current biodiversity spend,
and so over the last 24 months, the
cumulative reduction in
biodiversity spend is $133 million, and that
has biodiversity outcomes. Impacts on
biodiversity income, impacts across New Zealand
outcomes.
So yeah, when we get to the fund, if you were to draw
some dotted lines
or additional boxes above the dark blue bars, that's
what we want to do, is fill some of that with this new
fund, and that's where we seek full
cross-party support.
Next slide
Yes, so prevailing over biodiversity loss can't be solved the same
way as before. New Zealand households actually spend more on
cosmetics than biodiversity.
Collapse of all critical global ecosystems is a high risk rating.
Governments such as the UK government, Canadian government,
IPBS, WB, UN,
OECD, and
WEF. Living Planet Index is
-27 left from 50 years ago.
So it's declined and it's still declining.
Mm.
Urgent biodiversity investment is needed.
New Zealand's biodiversity investment has declined to
one point or 1,155 million in
2025/26. The cumulative
natural capital deferral increases are
133 million in two years. Prolonged deferral
is fiscal imprudence.
And just to, fiscal imprudence means
ongoing
financial mismanagement. And so for my
background's economics from New Zealand, London School of Economics, and
so we're saying reduce that fiscal imprudence and increase by
increasing investment. So it's a nice easy equation.
So I wanted to talk a little bit about the results of the research Ian's
done, and it really looked at all of the sectors
of government and local government and other sectors like primary and
business sectors, and how much is spent and where it's spent.
So this is the core of it. So-
Mm
... this is a very complicated diagram of course.
It's, I think we call it the worm diagram, but
the take homes are the size of the boxes on the left-hand side.
And DOC of course-
Goodness, I've got that on mine.
DOC of course, is the by far the largest expenditure, but you can see that
MPI and MFE are major contributors as well, and the
rest of government and regional unitary councils, of course, major contributors as
well. So,
but also the voluntary sectors. You've got community trusts and NGOs that are
making a massive amount of effort there, and they are
often supported by councils as well.
So it tends to be a whole ecosystem of effort that
goes into prioritizing at a very local level
what's important to the people in the communities of those areas,
and how do we deliver it together. And so that, the web side
of it, to me,
it's complicated and hard to understand, but it also gives it some resilience, I
think, as well. So, business and finance in there with $5
million. So it's obviously of interest, of broad interest to everyone.
In the next slide, I put the right-hand side into
an easier diagram that didn't have the worms on it, and that really
shows where it's being spent. So understandably, mostly on
conservation. But awareness of knowledge a lot on
biosecurity, which is understandable given the
impact that introduced pests have on our native ecosystems,
but also sustainable use, planning and finance, a little
bit on restoration and green economy.
And the P at the bottom is pollution management. That's only half a percent.
But,
these are all following, I think, your criteria, aren't they, that we have to
follow using the biofin process. So some of the language
used here isn't perhaps what New Zealand people would use.
Did you have any comments on that, Ian?
Yeah, so the key one out of all of these results was
restoration at 4%, which is
0.01% of GDP.
And so,
that's the area we've identified where we need to
invest, and improve our investment as the
economy grows. And so,
0.01%
goes a long way,
but if we were to double that to
0.02%, it would go a fantastic
amount of distance in terms of
maintaining and restoring what we call natural capital-
Mm
... in New Zealand. Yeah. So,
restoration is the one of the, of all of the biofin
categories where
it's been identified we need to do more.
Are we just doing questions at the end?
Sorry, just-
Yeah.
Just opening up for questions at the end.
We'll let them talk through-
Yeah
... the presentation,
and then we can have questions.
I think slides were-- I think we've only got four slides to go, but
yeah, this is, so this one's a summary of the recommendations that have come out
of the second
report that Ian's completed.
And firstly, can I just thank you for the cross-party support
you've given last time we were here, and that is incredibly important I
think,
just because biodiversity does affect all of us, and it's for all of us and for our
children. So that, I think, is our biggest ask is that can we
continue that? Secondly, of course, complete the assessment, do that third
report that we have to complete. We should have that done by Christmas,
maybe a bit after, depending on how we go.
We've also been asked to draft a natural capital policy, and Ian's probably well
placed to do that given his training.
And then we'll talk soon about this business case as well for a natural
capital fund, and I'll hand over to Ian on that.
So thanks, Chris. Just the bottom note there, in
terms of the fund, we're still
maintaining our ask for all
parties to commit to starting this fund at
25 million,
as a minimum manifesto commitment, which
equates to 2% of the current conservation
budget. That would be targeted at the
most effective, efficient biodiversity
outcomes that are currently unfunded in New
Zealand.
That equates to a $5 cup of
coffee each year, or
0.006% of GDP. Might only be
half a coffee now. Yeah, exactly. Depends on what coffee you
buy.
Yeah. So, and it's
back to that graph where we have economy
going up. What we're saying is
that this helps fill a bit of the gap, so that
as the economy grows, we invest more in
biodiversity. That's the principle.
And that provides a
step towards sustainable development.
So, we'll just move on to recommendation one, which is a
policy. That policy, and again, I'd just like to acknowledge Simon
Court. He
had
the vision to say, "Yeah, I can see we need that," so
I'd like to acknowledge him.
It simply says this is a natural capital asset
that we're investing in, like a building, like a school,
a hospital, a piece of machinery,
an airplane fleet, a set of trains, road.
It's an asset, so you maintain and restore it as
you get benefits from it. So, the real
key message there from the international community is, it's
like a relationship. If your partner is just take,
take, take, it's probably not going to work.
It's give and take, and that'll give you a good relationship, and
that's the relationship we want with New Zealand
biodiversity.
So, yeah, natural capital policy says it's an asset
and that we should reduce deferrals, as opposed to
increase deferrals.
Recommendation two
is the fund. We've sort of already talked about that.
Our key message there is it's
based on principles as opposed to
anything else. So, it's indexed to growth,
which provides the revenue stream.
The revenue side of the instrument of the
solution
is the most efficient thing you will have in New Zealand, because
it's indexed to
consumption, because consumption is the largest indirect
driver of biodiversity loss. That's not
disputed. Everyone
from World Bank through to OECD through to the UN,
it's an established fact.
So, as we increase consumption,
we invest more in biodiversity. So, it's indexed to GST
growth, which is a proxy for consumption growth.
So, just one last thing there. It's a balancing
loop.
So, the system's balancing loop. So, if you're just
consuming,
without investing, it's never going to work.
The other thing is it's independent.
So,
the best example of a fund that does this now is
the super fund.
They have their guardians. It's invested in the future.
It's a contribution. This is a fund which is
invested in the future. It's a contribution as we
consume.
The third thing there, voluntary contributions.
If the
other
organizations, which is going to be highly likely,
want to make a contribution and say, "Well, we want to leave something behind,"
this fund is what they can contribute to.
So, that's a
bonus.
Cost benefit targeting is an economic approach, and
how it works is, and we do it in New
Zealand already.
For those who know the Next Foundation, they're fantastic at this.
So,
that's where the costs are low and the
biodiversity benefits are high. That's where you invest.
So, it gives you the best cost-benefit ratio.
And so, every project that gets approved
must have that cost-benefit ratio to prove that it's doing
what it says it
will do, and then it's monitored.
The last bit here is you're investing in ecological
prospects for future generations.
The wording ecological prospects, I did get that from
Next. And it's
about making sure our children have the
same opportunities we had for
enjoying biodiversity.
And it's just where, again, this fund, we're talking
0.006%
of our GDP just to invest in future
generations.
It's
not even comparable to inflation, which happens every year
at over a cent a year.
So, initial results do show that that
significantly
outperforms things like credit schemes or plant a tree schemes.
It would be fair to say I've just been invited to Kenya to talk to the
UN about this new solution, because they can see
the potential in it, and they want other countries to know about it.
So, I leave on Sunday to go and present it to them.
Hopefully I don't come back with Ebola.
The last recommendations we're suggesting, we finished
the presentation. Thanks,
Barbara.
We finished the assessment. She's left the room, but I
really want to acknowledge Barbara Kuriger.
She has been incredible from the start of this journey as our-
You waited for her to leave.
I know, I'm just saying it behind her back.
She could tell it was about to happen.
She has been a fantastic, incredible,
amazing champion for this project across
parties from the start. So I just wanted to give that-
He spoke well of you too, Lam, before I came.
Yeah, he did speak highly of you. I have no doubt.
He's a specialist at doing it when you're not here.
PR 101, Ian.
No, my apologies, though. I mentioned to Ian that I would be racing
back from a speaking bit, and I am very sorry-
It's all good
... from the start.
It's so good to have you here, so thank you.
So yeah, finished the assessment.
So we've got two organizations who have participated in the
first stage. We really need their participation in the second stage because the
more they participate, the more they get out of it, and that's the Department of
Conservation and Ministry of Primary Industries.
Primary Industries because of biosecurity.
Department of Conservation because of their role in
biodiversity. Now, in the last
stage, they were hesitant to help because
they felt because I talked to ministers,
they felt like they shouldn't
necessarily be talking to me. So I just need some
support from Parliament to say, "Hey, it's all right to participate in the
next stage." So be very grateful for that steer.
They are keen as mustard, but they're just wondering why there
isn't support. So yeah, just wanted to mention that that would
really help because the more we work together, the
more robust our investment case will be.
Then the last recommendation, and I'm
very grateful for two pretty amazing people from the
Parliamentary Commissioner for the Environment,
is that we do this again, and so in
2029. So this is a strategic long-term thing.
It's not a short-term thing. And so we do it again,
do the assessment again,
and that
the Parliamentary Commissioner for the Environment would, in terms of their
purpose, they have the right purpose to lead this
with support from other organizations.
A lot of the support I got in terms of
understanding how I needed to reach out to government departments,
I was very grateful for the advice I was given from the
PCE.
That's our recommendations. I believe that's our presentation, and I'd
like to thank you
very much for your time, and we'd love to answer any questions you have.
Ta.
Oh, thank you very much, Ian, for that presentation.
Look, we have got a few questions. We will start with Lam.
Kia ora. Thank you so much.
First, just the initial question on your,
I don't know, as one of the-
Worm
... squares. No, not the worm, the squares. It was just basic.
You don't need to go back to it, actually.
Yep, I know the one. Yeah
But just the green economy part, it was only 3%.
I would think that would be a bigger-
Yeah, so-
... part. So what's the definition there, and what are you-
Yeah. So
Biophina is a United Nations methodology that's used in
133 countries. We use what's called an attribution
process. So the focus is on biodiversity,
including biosecurity. So if I'm
spending $100 million on
solar panels, we would count, say,
3%, 4%, 5% of that towards
biodiversity.
Mm-hmm.
Compared to, say, a next model where
they're
doing work on directly with biodiversity or
Department of Conservation's conservation budget.
We would go 80%, 90%, 100% of the attribution
of that $100 million would be counted.
Okay.
So that's the reason, is how we attribute the
investment-
Okay
... specifically for biodiversity.
Thank you.
And Priyanka, yes.
My question related to that was then, given
that the green economy spend is 3%, restoration is 4%,
you mentioned that restoration is really where we should be
investing in. And I wanted to
know why. Is that because
a cost-benefit analysis there, that every dollar that you
spend in restoration yields more directly to
biodiversity protection, or was there a different reason for that?
Yeah, that's a great question. And
initial testing, yes, you're going to get a much higher
cost-benefit ratio from that investment.
It's also an area where
we're not improving the asset, and New Zealand's in that position now where we need
to be improving that asset. And so it's also
purpose-driven. It's not to say, for example, green
economy doesn't need more investment, because it certainly does.
But for biodiversity outcomes, that's where you're
going to get bang for buck, or money.
Grant, you've got a supplement
It's got support on that also into this restoration bit.
So I'm just curious how you
got your figures about
restoration from, because does it include
what private people are doing? How would you know?
Some of the work that, for example, is done on farms.
Mm.
How was that? I'm just curious.
All right.
Yeah.
Good question.
So I'm going to use a phrase here, which I still snuck
into the report without anyone telling me off too much.
So the
primary industry spend, which is about 55 million, comes
from Beef and Lamb have really good figures.
They do an annual environmental expenditure, so Beef and Lamb provided
that,
or Sheep and Beef as they like me to call it.
And so fisheries, that came
from, is it Seafood New Zealand?
Mm.
Dairy came from Dairy New Zealand. So those numbers came from them.
The private sector,
in terms of the NGOs,
getting those figures was worse than drinking
a warm cup of cat sick.
It really was.
That's the first time I've read that in a report.
So there's 1,200 NGOs registered on the
Charity Services register. Anything over
a million dollars, we went through their annual
report. So that took quite a while.
Ian, can I just mention too, so from Beef and Lamb's point of view,
I'm a monitored farm.
Yep.
So what happens there is that every year I sit down with
someone from Beef and Lamb. They go through line by line my
financials, and we identify what was spent
on biodiversity, all that side of things.
So it is quite a thorough-
Example of fencing, pest control-
Yep
... planting-
Yes
... that type of thing.
Anything else on this?
Yep.
Celia.
Thank you very much. That's great for
farming landowners.
Is there anything collected about what people who've got basically carbon
farms or are small land holders that aren't
members of those large groups?
You mean life season spark holders are what you're talking about?
Hmm?
Life season spark holders.
Oh, season.
Oh, my.
Oh, God.
So unless we captured it under the
non-governmental organizations as investment, we
weren't able to capture those.
You wouldn't have that. That's fine. I couldn't see how you could.
Yeah. Yeah.
But that's interesting. Okay.
So what we also captured though, as part of the NGOs,
is an estimate of $49 million worth
of voluntary hours. That's an underestimate.
Yeah.
So New Zealanders are saying, "We want this work
done anyway."
And did-
Yeah. Yep
... and did that include Predator Free New Zealand Trust?
Correct. Yes.
Okay.
Yeah, Predator Free Trust.
The whole lot.
And all, yeah, all the work that Nex does with them. Yeah.
So Jesse Morgan and the rest as well.
Catchment groups.
Sorry?
You do catchment groups?
Okay. Yes. So Chris can talk to
the council numbers if you want.
Yeah. Just-
Yes. It's supported by either NPI on Farm or
regional councils or both.
Mm.
Catchment groups are very well covered, I think.
Okay.
Mm.
And I was thinking to your question, a lot of people
will be seeking funding
from councils, whether regional or otherwise, and also
from trusts. Like in our region we have Bay Trust and
also some energy trusts who've increasingly got into the space-
Mm
... of environmental contributions.
So quite often you'll find
people who are doing work in the environment will be seeking
co-funding or contributions.
Mm.
And in fact, that became a bit of a problem for Ian, because then we had to go
through and make sure we weren't double counting it.
Yeah. Yeah.
Because it was counted once by regional council, once by Bay Trust, and
then-
Mm
... the landowner might have put the same number in there.
So that was quite a rigorous process, as I recall, going through-
Mm. Well, actually-
... quite a handful of them
... useful.
Yeah.
Okay.
I did wonder though why you only put
regional and unitary, because I know at least in Eden
and Wellington city councils put in a fairly walloping
amount of rate payers' money.
So the-
Did that get included, just the title or?
So the answer to that is lack of resources.
So had to focus on what I could add up.
Okay. No.
So I couldn't include the territorials or the locals.
Where we have been able to capture some of their numbers is if
they've made contributions to an NGO,
then we capture it there. So NGOs spend 100
million a year plus the 49 million-
Mm
... on voluntary hours, but their actual spend is something like
238 million because they also get additional
funding from regional councils and central government
that they deliver. They are actually the second biggest delivery
body in New Zealand.
Mm.
Thank you.
I'll come back with more questions.
Yeah, we've just got a couple of other questions around the table. So Priyanka.
Thanks. I had a question when I read your
report, Ian, on work like
what Botham School's doing around credits, nature credits-
Yep
... financing. I see in your PowerPoint presentation as well that you've
said that your fund is more effective than credits.
Yep.
So wanting to understand that a little bit better, and also work out how
existing work in that space fits into this.
Yep.
Mm.
So credits have, so
by VCD projects, the one way to look at it, just one way, is
those projects are there already.
Mm.
And so if you've got $100, you want $100 going into
that project. And so the administration on the
fund is Is kept very low so that the
$100 go in.
With credit schemes, they are usually attached
to conditions, usually commercial
conditions. They also have an admin cost
that goes over the top of it, same with offsets.
And also, there's also the where are we finding the
money from. And so that's a massive cost internationally as well.
And so just to also put credits into the global scheme.
So biodiversity finance across the glo-
globally is over 100 billion.
You've got United Nations environment
programme measure it every year.
Of that portion,
18% is private,
82% is public. So most of the innovation is actually happening in
the public sector. The reason for that is because biodiversity
has public good characteristics-
Mm
... like policing,
some parts of the health system,
governance. So it's public. And so of that, there's
5% in offsets and credits, and of that, I think
1% is credits internationally.
Mm-hmm.
But there's definitely opportunity to grow the market.
Yeah.
Right? But you're always going to have a lot of
cost on that. And talking to the biodiversity
credit firms that are doing it in New Zealand-
Mm-hmm
... they're saying it's a lot of administration at the moment.
So is there a way to include that in your
fund sort of model, or is this a parallel model?
Yes. So
in terms, yes and no. So the yes is it'll be included
in the BioFin assessment.
It won't be included in the fund because it's a separate thing.
Okay.
So the overall funding from New Zealand will be a mix of
funding tools.
Mm-hmm.
The fund will just be, like I said, it's just
2% of the total.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah. But it'll be highly targeted in
principle to do cost benefit targeting.
Yeah.
Thank you. Look, we have got a question from Sam Fundel.
Oh, yeah.
I have all these wonderful bay boys here. It's good.
Hey, you mentioned there about the 82%.
I'm assuming you meant that that's spending from the,
is that of the spending pool? That's from the public sector.
Correct. Yeah, so. Yeah, correct.
And generally that's from
green bonds, right? Where they'll borrow from investors, the
government will borrow from investors, pay them a coupon, and then use that
money to
finance different environmental projects.
So the answer to the question is that's a small
part of it.
Oh, okay. Yeah.
So there's at the moment, there's
150 different methods that the international
community raises finance, where in New Zealand we've got, say,
five or six key ones like rates and doing credits
and votes, stuff like that.
Okay.
NGO. So they do bonds, they do
off all sorts of stuff. A lot of the government funding
internationally is similar to our votes.
Okay.
So it's a government allocation for a purpose.
As you no doubt know, one of the things we'll look at in New
Zealand is green bonds, and using that
green bonds revenue or portion of it
for biodiversity.
Mm-hmm.
I think that's a good idea.
We-
And, Cameron.
Oh, straight into me. Thank you.
Yeah.
Thank you.
And then I'll go to Lan.
Lovely. Okay. Well, my question, thank you.
While speaking, I've just got a question about, this committee's just been through
a large process on the new planning and natural environment bills.
And in there, there's the regulatory relief function.
Do you think that your BioFin methodology will be
a way for councils to
accurately-ish measure the
regulatory burdens they're putting on when they go to make a planning measure or
regulation on a private landowner?
And a way we can value
other things, like whether this is justified, whether there's another way to do
it.
Do you see this methodology being utilized in that regard?
So I think they're complementary things rather than
the fund will do that. So the fund is-
Well, that's about the methodology more, but-
Yeah
... sure.
Yeah. Yeah.
Sorry, rather the fund, but yeah.
So,
the purpose of the fund is to improve the asset.
So that's the purpose of the fund. So
what you're possibly talking about is research and
policy, that'll be our,
our focus will be on restoration-
I guess I'm asking, like the fund is going to have to know what it's doing, right?
You're going to have to have-
Yeah
... methodologies to figure out biodiversity values, whether
this is the best path to go.
Yeah.
Like the method. And so,
is this going to be something that's open to councils to be able to use?
Do you think it becomes a recognizable process?
Yes. So yes, the answer to that question, yes.
Yeah. Excellent.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm. Which was kind of my question actually, was around how the RMA and changing
the resource management system,
how BioFin sits alongside that or how
you kind of see that.
Do you want to talk to that a bit?
Yeah, it's a really interesting question, and I think some of us are still
wrapping our heads around-
Mm
... the significance of the decisions that have been
just released. And
I
think we're talking about apples and oranges though.
Mm-hmm.
So one thing is a regulatory, how do
we regulate for biodiversity, and I think that's a very complex
problem for New Zealand, and the RMA tried one way, and
now we're going to try it a different way. But this is non-regulatory.
This is investing in the environment.
No, I think that's part of the-
So this is more like the predator free thing.
But that's part of
the options in the new system is saying-
You don't necessarily have to regulate.
You can try these other ways, more consents, more
development opportunities, or at least have investment come in.
Mm.
So do you-- Yeah. Obviously something you'd like to say, you're trying to get your
head around it-
Yeah
... and trying to work with it.
It could work. Mm.
But so it is complementary-
It's, it's-
... in that sense, yes.
Yes.
Complementary. Excellent.
Um, Lam, your question. Yeah, no.
Unworkable. But-
Oh, in your opinion.
Interested in, coming back to the fund,
I know governments have different priorities, and they're
always going to be stretched for money.
What is sort of your selling point in terms
of... Because, for example, the Community Environment Fund was
scrapped by this government.
What is the selling point of this fund
and, because it's pri-- If I understand it correctly, it's like
prioritizing the low-hanging fruit or like the biggest
bang for buck kind of projects versus a
general slash community fund that will actually fund
grassroots restoration and biodiversity.
How would you describe the difference?
So the purpose of this fund is
to invest in biodiversity so that your core...
And keeping in mind, it's 0.006% of
GDP, so we're not talking
a huge allocation of our economy.
It doesn't prohibit, nor should
it prohibit, having community funds where you're getting
wider benefits. I think that's fantastic.
This fund will be very targeted,
similar to the next model in some ways.
Can I just jump in there from a practical point of view?
Sorry, I don't .
Yeah, that's good.
So, on the ground, a fund like this is
really good in the fact that, A, there's not going to be a
whole lot of bureaucracy in the middle.
One of the biggest things about
biodiversity is that so often,
people who are working on the ground get tied up in
admin, in a whole lot of other things, and it doesn't put trees in the ground.
Mm.
It doesn't do trapping. It doesn't do all those sort of things.
A fund like this is going to sit out the independent, just like QE2, which
is complementary to this.
Mm-hmm.
And it'll mean you're going to get a lot more bang for your buck.
That's the really-
And ongoing continuity-
On, yes, exactly
... on the ground, right? Yeah.
It's not going to fall off a cliff each time a government changes, that sort of
thing.
Yeah.
That's another really important thing about biodiversity.
The minute we stop, it goes backwards 100 miles an hour.
Yeah. Mm.
So, this is a fund that'll keep things moving forward.
And then just a quick follow-up,
because I know we're getting close to the end of time.
You asked specifically for a steer, like a
steer from the committee about something.
I'm sorry, I wasn't following what...
Like what can we actually
do out of this meeting that would actually help what you were
describing?
So it goes back to those four recommendations.
Number one, support our government, particularly those
two government agencies feel like they can participate.
So that's number one.
But does that look like a formal letter to them? What does that mean?
That would help a lot-
Sorry
... is formal communication saying, "Hey, work with Biofin."
That's all it needs to do-
Okay
... to complete the final stage. So that's number one.
Mm-hmm.
And number two,
recognize that to get the full value out of this, we do it
again in three years' time-
Mm-hmm
... through the PCE. Number three, the natural capital policy,
just acknowledge we're doing that, and that will get reviewed by
relevant government agencies. And number four, the
fund is the big thing that is in your gift, is
to, for, and that's why we're asking for
reiteration of cross-party support to set up
the fund because that means a manifesto commitment.
Mm. So do you mean at a party level? What do you
mean when you say manifesto level?
Correct.
You want to see us echoing what you're asking for?
Yeah.
Okay.
Just-
Just to clarify.
Correct.
Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you.
Just on your point around DOC,
Ian,
that would impact DOC's work program, and generally, that
directive comes from the minister.
Is this a conversation you've had with the minister around DOC supporting this
work?
So yeah, the Minister of Conservation knows what we're doing.
Yeah.
But no communication has been made to DOC, and so
that's where we need support, is to get a, just
even a two sentences-
Yeah
... on letterhead saying, "Continue to participate with
Biofin to complete the last Biofin stage."
So that's all we're asking. And the same for
MPI through possibly Minister Hogan.
Mm.
Yeah. Just two simple communications or an email, I don't
mind.
Have you asked the minister to do that first with DOC?
So
we've asked, and so the minister has said,
"Go and talk to them." They've said, "Well, where's the formal comm, yeah,
communication from the minister?" So,
it would help to
have formal communication, even if it's just an email.
And then, yeah.
Okay, thank you.
Celia.
Thank you very much, Catherine.
Yeah.
I'm just following up on that one. If the committee is, without
committing ourselves, particularly at this election time, but
interested in this proposal, I would suggest that
we endorse our chair writing to both of those ministers saying
that we are
interested and supportive in-
principle-
Mm
... of seeing this proceed, and
that doesn't mean that any particular party
puts anything in their budget for the manifesto.
But I think it would be helpful for it not to just get
dropped through the election and coalition negotiations, and all that sort of
thing. So Catherine, if you'd be kind enough to think about that for a
moment. I do have a brief question.
One,
I hear what you say about the complexity of the admin for both
carbon credits and biodiversity additionality.
But you're not saying stop work on that.
No.
You're saying that goes along in parallel.
So what Minister Hoggard announced in June,
giving some ticks to perhaps catchment level that
farmers and other landowners
get something for what they're doing, would still work in parallel, and you
would start to count that in the dollars that came in.
100%.
Yeah. Okay.
Yeah, so that's a really important thing to reiterate,
is this fund is only a small piece of it,
but we're making an early recommendation because we know how
effective it will be,
based on the work we've done.
The overall investment in our natural
capital needs credits.
Okay.
It needs boats, it needs this fund, it needs
NGOs. This is just an early
recommendation that we're asking for commitment for the
'27, '28 financial year.
So yeah, just to reiterate, as part of the
final stage, we will actually estimate what we think credits will give us.
Okay.
And so those people who are credit
specialists can provide us their numbers.
Mm. Look, thank you, Ian. I think that's a good spot to end it
on, and obviously you can hear the bells.
But look, we really appreciate your presentation today.
And you've traversed some really good areas that
we do want to consider as a committee and, we will
make those considerations salient, and we thank you
for your time today.
Thank you very, very much-
And I know-
... for the committee's time. We're very grateful. Thank you.
Brilliant. Thank you.
Thank you.
That's all right.
So next up-